<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-dnsop-extended-error-0.1"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="draft-wkumari-dnsop-extended-error">Extended DNS
    Errors</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Evan Hunt" initials="E." surname="Hunt">
      <organization>ISC</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter St</street>

          <city>Redwood City, CA</city>

          <code>94063</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>each@isc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roy Arends" initials="R." surname="Arends">
      <organization>Nominet</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>TBD</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wes Hardaker" initials="W." surname="Hardaker">
      <organization>USC/ISI</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 382</street>

          <city>Davis, VA</city>

          <code>95617</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ietf@hardakers.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="January" year="2015"/>

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>template</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines an extensible method to return additional
      information about the cause of DNS errors. The primary use case is to
      extend SERVFAIL to provide additional information about the cause of
      DNSSEC failures, but it can be used to annotate many other DNS
      errors.
      [wjh: I think we have to take on all errors, not just DNSSEC]
      [wjh #2: can it annotate non-error messages too?  If not, why not?]
      </t>

      <t>[ Note: I always have a hard time with EDNS terminology - I'm saying
      that Extended DNS Errors are carried as EDNS Options, but is this
      correct? They are optional TLVs in "options" in RDATA in OPTion RR , but
      that's not readable. ]</t>

      <t>[ Open question: The document currently defines a registry for
      errors. It has also been suggested that the option also carry human
      readable (text) messages, so allow the server admin to provide
      additional annotation (e.g: "example.com pointed their NS at us. No idea
      why...", "We don't provide recursive DNS to 192.0.2.0. Please stop
      asking...", "Have you tried Acme Anvil and DNS? We do DNS right..." (!).
      Please let us know if you think text is needed, or if a 16bit FCFS
      registry is expressive enough. ]</t>

      <t>[ Open question: This document discusses extended *errors*, but it
      has been suggested that this could be used to also annotate *non-error*
      messages. The authors do not think that this is a good idea, but could
      be persuaded otherwise. ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and background">
      <t>There are many reasons that a DNS query may fail, some of them
      transient, some permanent; some can be resolved by querying another
      server, some (e.g DNSSEC bogus) are likely best handled by stopping
      resolution.
      [wjh: no: bogus should continue to other servers too]
      Unfortunately, the error signals that a DNS server can return are very
      limited, and are not very expressive. This means that applications and
      resolvers often have to "guess" at what the issue is -  e.g the
      answer was marked REFUSED because of a lame delegation, 
      or because there is a lame delegation or because the nameserver is still
      starting up and loading zones? Is a SERVFAIL a DNSSEC validation issue, or
      is the nameserver experiencing a bad hair day?</t>

      <t>A good example of issues that would benefit by additional
      error information is an error caused by a DNSSEC validation issue.
      When a stub resolver queries a DNSSEC bogus
      name (using a validating resolver), their machine receives a SERVFAIL
      in response. Unfortunately, SERVFAIL is used to signal many sorts of DNS
      errors, and so the stub resolver simply asks the next
      configured DNS resolver.
      <!-- again: this is still correct in many cases even if you do
           know the error in question; stale auth servers cause this
           problem and the right thing to do is ask the next guy,
           which is hopefully less stale -wjh -->
      <!-- this next sentence makes no sense and I can't fix it -wjh -->
      This may result in [one of] two outcomes:
      either the next resolver does not validate, in which case the user
      resolves the name (defeating the protection provided by DNSSEC); or it
      does, and they get a failure that is largely incomprehensible to the
      average user.</t>

      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to extend (or annotate) DNS
      errors to provide additional information about the cause of the error.
      This information can be used by the resolver to make a decision whether
      to retry or not, or by technical users attempting to debug issues.</t>

      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to extend (or annotate)
      DNS errors to provide additional information about the cause of
      the error.  This information can be used by a resolver to make a
      decision whether or no to retry, or by administrators and
      technical users attempting to debug issues.</t>

      <t>Here is a reference to an "external" (non-RFC / draft) thing: (<xref
      target="IANA.AS_Numbers"/>). And this is a link to an ID:<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-sidr-iana-objects"/>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Extended Error EDNS0 option format">
      <t>This draft uses an EDNS0 ([RFC2671]) option to include extended error
      (ExtError) information in DNS messages. The option is structured as
      follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                                             1   1   1   1   1   1
     0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7   8   9   0   1   2   3   4   5  
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
0: |                            OPTION-CODE                        |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
2: |                           OPTION-LENGTH                       |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
4: | R |                         FLAGS                             |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
6: |                             CODE                              |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>OPTION-CODE, 2 octets (Defined in [RFC6891]), for ExtError is
          TBD.</t>

          <t>OPTION-LENGTH, 2 octets ((Defined in [RFC6891]) contains the
          length of the payload (everything after OPTION-LENGTH) in
          octets. [um, can't we say "and should be 4"? --wjh]
          </t>

          <t>FLAGS, 2 octets.</t>

          <t>CODE, 2 octets.</t>
          <!-- you know someone will want user strings too -->
        </list></t>

      <t>Currently the only defined flag is the R flag. <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="R - Retry">The R (or Retry) flag provides a hint to the
          receiver if it should retry the query, possibly by querying another
          server. If the R bit is set (1), the sender believes that retrying
          the query may provide a successful answer next time;
          if the R bit is clear
          (0), the sender believes that it should not ask another
          server.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The remaining bits in the flags field MUST be set to 0 by the sender
      and SHOULD be ignored by the receiver.</t>

      <t>Code: A code point into the IANA "Extended DNS Errors" registry.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of the Extended DNS Error option">
      <t>The Extended DNS Error (EDE) is an EDNS option. It can be included
      in any error response (SERVFAIL, NXDOMAIN, REFUSED, etc) to a
      query that includes an EDNS option. This document includes a set
      of initial codepoints (and requests to the IANA to add them to
      the registry), but is extensible via the IANA registry to allow
      additional error codes to be defined in the future [by standards
      action, or what? --wjh].</t>

      <t>The R (Retry) flag provides a hint (or suggestion) as to what
      the receiver may want to do with this annotated error. The
      mechanism is specifically designed to be extensible, and so
      implementations may receive EDE codes that it does not
      understand. The R flag allows implementations to make a decision
      as to what to do if it receives a response with an unknown code
      - retry or drop the query. Note that this flag is only a
      suggestion or hint. Receivers can choose to ignore this
      hint.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Defined Extended DNS Errors">
      <t>This document defines some initial EDE codes. The mechanism is
      intended to be extensible, and additional codepoints will be registered
      in the "Extended DNS Errors" registry. This document provides
      suggestions for the R flag, but the originating server may ignore these
      recommendations if it knows better.</t>

      <section title="Extended DNS Error Code 1 - DNSSEC Bogus">
        <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but validation
        ended in the Bogus state.</t>

        <t>Usually attached to SERVFAIL messages. The R flag should be
        set.</t> <!-- when is not? ever? -->
      </section>

      <section title="Extended DNS Error Code 2 - DNSSEC Indeterminite">
        <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but validation
        ended in the Indeterminate state.</t>

        <t>Usually attached to SERVFAIL messages. The R flag should be
        set.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Extended DNS Error Code 3 - Lame">
        <t>An authoritative resolver that receives a query (with the RD bit
        clear) for a domain for which it is not authoritative SHOULD include
        this EDE code in the REFUSED response.</t>

        <t>Implementations should not set the R flag in this case (another
        nameserver might not be lame).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Extended DNS Error Code 4 - Prohibited">
        <t>An authoritative or recursive resolver that receives a query from
        an "unauthorized" client can annotate its REFUSED message with this
        code. Examples of "unauthorized" clients are recursive queries from IP
        addresses outside the network, blacklisted IP addresses, etc.</t>

        <t>Implementations SHOULD allow operators to define what to set the R
        flag to in this case.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Extended DNS Error Code 5 - Ratelimited">
        <t>[ Ed: This might be a bad idea. It is intended to allow servers
        under a DoS (for example a random subdomain attack) to signal to
        recursive clients that they are being abusive and should back off.
        This may be a bad idea -- it may "complete the attack", it may be
        spoofable (by anyone who could also do a MITM style attack), etc. ]
        </t>

        <t>A nameserver which is under excessive load (for example, because it
        is experiencing a DoS) may annotate any answer with this code.</t>

        <t>It is RECOMMENDED that implementations set the R flag in this case,
        but may allow operators to define what to set the R flag to.</t>

        <t>[ agreed: bad idea -wjh ]</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[This section under construction ]</t>

      <t>This document defines a new EDNS(0) option, entitled "Extended DNS
      Error", assigned a value of TBD1 from the "DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT)"
      registry [to be removed upon publication:
      [http://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters/dns-parameters.xhtml#dns-parameters-11]</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Value  Name                 Status    Reference
-----  ----------------     ------    ------------------
 TBD   Extended DNS Error    TBD       [ This document ]]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Data Tag Name Length Meaning ---- ---- ------ ------- TBD1 FooBar N
      FooBar server</t>

      <t>The IANA is requested to create and maintain the "Extended DNS Error
      codes" registry. The codepoint space is broken into 3 ranges:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>1 - 16384: Specification required.</t>

          <t>16385 - 65000: First Come First Served</t>

          <t>65000 - 65534: Experimental / Private use</t>
        </list>The codepoints 0, 65535 are reserved.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Open questions">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="1">Can this be included in *any* response or only
          responses to requests that included an EDNS option? Resolvers are
          supposed to ignore additional. EDNS capable ones are supposed to
          simply ignore unknown options.</t>

          <t hangText="2">Can this be applied to *any* response, or only error
          responses?</t>

          <t>Only ones signaling EDNS support; all the EDNS code
          points were designed to only be responded to when clients
          indicated they could handle them.  -- 95% sure wjh</t>

        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>DNSSEC is being deployed - unfortunately a significant number of
      clients (TODO: Link to Geoff H stats), when receiving a SERVFAIL from a
      validating resolver because of a DNSSEC validaion issue simply ask the
      next (non-validating) resolver in their list, and do don't get any of
      the protections which DNSSEC should provide. This is very similar to a
      kid asking his mother if he can have another cookie. When the mother
      says "No, it will ruin your dinner!", going off and asking his (more
      permissive) father and getting a "Yes, sure, cookie!".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank Geoff Huston. They also vaguely remember
      discussing this with a number of people over the years, but have
      forgotten who all they were -- if you were one of them, and are not
      listed, please let us know and we'll acknowledge you.</t>

      <t>I also want to thank the band Infected Mushroom for providing a good
      background soundtrack (and to see if I can get away with this!)</t>

      <t>Another author would like to thank the band "Mushroom Infectors"</t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <reference anchor="IANA.AS_Numbers"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/as-numbers">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Autonomous System (AS) Numbers">Autonomous System
          (AS) Numbers</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to -01;</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Placeholder to remind me to include changelog.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
