<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-extended-error-05"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="draft-ietf-dnsop-extended-error">Extended DNS
    Errors</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Evan Hunt" initials="E." surname="Hunt">
      <organization>ISC</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter St</street>

          <city>Redwood City, CA</city>

          <code>94063</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>each@isc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roy Arends" initials="R." surname="Arends">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
        </postal>

        <email>roy.arends@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wes Hardaker" initials="W." surname="Hardaker">
      <organization>USC/ISI</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 382</street>

          <city>Davis, CA</city>

          <code>95617</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ietf@hardakers.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David C Lawrence" initials="D." surname="Lawrence">
      <organization>Oracle + Dyn</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>150 Dow St</street>

          <city>Manchester, NH</city>

          <code>03101</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tale@dd.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="March" year="2019"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines an extensible method to return
      additional information about the cause of DNS errors. Though
      created primarily to extend SERVFAIL to provide additional
      information about the cause of DNS and DNSSEC failures, the
      Extended DNS Errors option defined in this document allows all
      response types to contain extended error information.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and background">
      <t>There are many reasons that a DNS query may fail, some of
      them transient, some permanent; some can be resolved by querying
      another server, some are likely best handled by stopping
      resolution.  Unfortunately, the error signals that a DNS server
      can return are very limited, and are not very expressive. This
      means that applications and resolvers often have to "guess" at
      what the issue is - e.g. was the answer marked REFUSED because
      of a lame delegation, or because the nameserver is still
      starting up and loading zones? Is a SERVFAIL a DNSSEC validation
      issue, or is the nameserver experiencing a bad hair day?</t>

      <t>A good example of issues that would benefit by additional error
      information are errors caused by DNSSEC validation issues. When a stub
      resolver queries a DNSSEC bogus name (using a validating resolver), the
      stub resolver receives only a SERVFAIL in response. Unfortunately,
      SERVFAIL is used to signal many sorts of DNS errors, and so the stub
      resolver simply asks the next configured DNS resolver. The result of
      trying the next resolver is one of two outcomes: either the next
      resolver also validates, a SERVFAIL is returned again, and the user gets
      an (largely) incomprehensible error message; or the next resolver is not
      a validating resolver, and the user is returned a potentially harmful
      result.</t>

      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to extend (or annotate) DNS
      errors to provide additional information about the cause of the error.
      When properly authenticated, this information can be used by the
      resolver to make a decision regarding whether or not to retry or it can
      be used or by technical users attempting to debug issues.</t>

      <t>These extended error codes are specially useful when received
      by resolvers, to return to stub resolvers or to downstream
      resolvers. Authoritative servers MAY parse and use them, but
      most error codes would make no sense for them.  Authoritative
      servers may need to generate extended error codes though.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Extended Error EDNS0 option format">
      <t>This draft uses an EDNS0 ([RFC2671]) option to include
      Extended DNS Error (EDE) information in DNS messages. The option
      is structured as follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                                             1   1   1   1   1   1
     0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7   8   9   0   1   2   3   4   5  
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
0: |                            OPTION-CODE                        |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
2: |                           OPTION-LENGTH                       |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
4: | R |                          RESERVED                         |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
6: | RESPONSE-CODE |             INFO-CODE                         |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
8: |                             EXTRA-TEXT                        |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t>Field definition details:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>OPTION-CODE, 2 octets (defined in [RFC6891]), for EDE is
          TBD. [RFC Editor: change TBD to the proper code once
          assigned by IANA.]</t>

          <t>OPTION-LENGTH, 2 octets ((defined in [RFC6891]) contains
          the length of the payload (everything after OPTION-LENGTH)
          in octets and should be 4 plus the length of the EXTRA-TEXT
          section (which may be a zero-length string).</t>

          <t>The RETRY flag, 1 bit; the RETRY bit (R) indicates a flag
          defined for use in this specification.</t>

          <t>The RESERVED bits, 15 bits: these bits are reserved for
          future use, potentially as additional flags.  The RESERVED
          bits MUST be set to 0 by the sender and MUST be ignored by
          the receiver.</t>

	  <t>RESPONSE-CODE, 4 bits. (Note: RESPONSE-CODE and INFO-CODE
	  together comprise a 2-octet field in network byte order, of which
	  RESPONSE-CODE is the most significant 4 bits.)</t>

	  <t>INFO-CODE, 12 bits. (The least significant 12 bits of the
	  combined 2-octet field described above.)</t>

          <t>EXTRA-TEXT, a variable length, UTF-8 encoded, text field
          that may hold additional textual information.</t>
        </list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Use of the Extended DNS Error option">
      <t>The Extended DNS Error (EDE) is an EDNS option. It can be included
      in any response (SERVFAIL, NXDOMAIN, REFUSED, etc) to a query that
      includes OPT Pseudo-RR <xref target="RFC6891" />. A sender MUST NOT
      include more than one Extended DNS Error option per message;
      additional Extended DNS Error options after the first one MUST be
      ignored by the receiver.</t>

      <t>This document includes a set of initial codepoints (and requests
      to the IANA to add them to the registry), but is extensible via the
      IANA registry to allow additional error and information codes to be
      defined in the future.</t>

      <t>The fields of the Extended DNS Error option are defined
      further in the following sub-sections.</t>

      <section title="The R (Retry) flag">
          <t>The R (Retry) flag provides a hint as to what the
          receiver may want to do with this annotated
          error. Specifically, the R (or Retry) flag provides a hint
          to the receiver that it should retry the query to another
          server. If the R bit is set (1), the sender believes that
          retrying the query may provide a successful answer next
          time; if the R bit is clear (0), the sender believes that
          the resolver should not ask another server.</t>

          <t>The mechanism is specifically designed to be extensible,
          and so implementations may receive EDE codes that it does
          not understand. The R flag allows implementations to make a
          decision as to what to do if it receives a response with an
          unknown code - retry or drop the query. Note that this flag
          is only a suggestion. Unless a protective transport
          mechanism (like TSIG <xref target="RFC2845"/> or (D)TLS xref
          target="RFC7858"/>, <xref
          target="RFC8094"/>) is used, the bit's value could have have
          been altered by a person-in-the-middle. Receivers can choose
          to ignore this hint.  See the security considerations for
          additional considerations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The RESPONSE-CODE field">
	  <t>This 4-bit value SHOULD be a copy of the RCODE from the
	  primary DNS packet. RESPONSE-CODEs MAY use a different RCODE
	  to provide additional or better information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The INFO-CODE field">
          <t>This 12-bit value provides the additional context for the
          RESPONSE-CODE value. This combination of the RESPONSE-CODE
          and the INFO-CODE serve as a joint-index into the IANA
          "Extended DNS Errors" registry.</t>

          <t>Note to implementers: the combination of the
          RESPONSE-CODE and INFO-CODE fits within a 16-bit field,
          allowing implementers the choice of treating the combination
          as either two separate values, as defined in this document,
          or as a single 16-bit integer as long as the results are
          deterministic.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The EXTRA-TEXT field">
          <t>The UTF-8-encoded, EXTRA-TEXT field may be zero-length,
          or may hold additional information useful to network
          operators.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Defined Extended DNS Errors">
      <t>This document defines some initial EDE codes. The mechanism
      is intended to be extensible, and additional code-points can be
      registered in the "Extended DNS Errors" registry. This document
      provides suggestions for the R flag, but the originating server
      may ignore these recommendations if it knows better.</t>

      <t>The RESPONSE-CODE and the INFO-CODE from the EDE EDNS option is used
      to serve as a double index into the "Extended DNS Error codes" IANA
      registry, the initial values for which are defined in the following
      sub-sections.</t>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NOERROR(0)">
        <section anchor="errbaddnskeyalg"
                 title="NOERROR Extended DNS Error Code 1 - Unsupported                           DNSKEY Algorithm">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but a DNSKEY
          RRSET contained only unknown algorithms. The R flag should be
          set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errbaddsalg"
                 title="NOERROR Extended DNS Error Code 2 - Unsupported                           DS Algorithm">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but a DS
          RRSET contained only unknown algorithms. The R flag should be
          set.</t>
        </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NOERROR(3)">
        <section anchor="stalenoerror"
	         title="NOERROR Extended DNS Error Code 3 - Stale Answer">
          <t>The resolver was unable to resolve answer within its time
          limits and decided to answer with a previously cached data
          instead of answering with an error.  This is typically
          caused by problems on authoritative side, possibly as result
          of a DoS attack. The R flag should not be set, since
          retrying is likely to create additional load without
          yielding a more fresh answer.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

        <section anchor="forgedanswer"
                 title="NOERROR Extended DNS Error Code 4 - Forged answer">
          <t>For policy reasons (legal obligation, or malware
          filtering, for instance), an answer was forged.  The R flag
          should not be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errindeterminate"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 5 - DNSSEC Indeterminate">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but
          validation ended in the Indeterminate state. The R flag should not
          be set.</t>
        </section>

      </section>



      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: SERVFAIL(2)">
        <section anchor="errbogus"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 1 - DNSSEC Bogus">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but
          validation ended in the Bogus state. The R flag should not be
          set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errexpired"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 2 - Signature Expired">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, a
          signature in the validation chain was expired. The R flag
          should not be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errprior"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 3 - Signature Not Yet Valid">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but the
          signatures received were not yet valid. The R flag should not be
          set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errnodnskey"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 4 - DNSKEY missing">
          <t>A DS record existed at a parent, but no supported
          matching DNSKEY record could be found for the child. The R
          flag should not be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errnorrsig"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 5 - RRSIGs missing">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but no
          RRSIGs could be found for at least one RRset where RRSIGs were
          expected.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errnozonekey"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 6 - No Zone Key Bit Set">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but no Zone
          Key Bit was set in a DNSKEY.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="noauth"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 7 - No
                        Reachable Authority">
          <t>The resolver could not reach any of the authoritative name servers
          (or they refused to reply).  The R flag should be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="nonsec"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 8 - NSEC Missing">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perform DNSSEC validation, but the
          requested data was missing and a covering NSEC or NSEC3 was not
          provided. The R flag should be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="cachederror"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 9 - Cached Error">
          <t>The resolver has cached SERVFAIL for this query without
          additional information.  Th R flag should be set.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="notready"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 10 - Not Ready">
          <t>The server is unable to answer the query as it is not
          fully up and functional yet.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="notspecified"
                 title="SERVFAIL Extended DNS Error Code 11 - Not Specified">
	  <t>A generic code which may be used when a SERVFAIL response does
	  not fall into any of the other categories. The R flag should not be
	  set.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NOTIMP(4)">
	<section anchor="deprecated"
	         title="NOTIMP Extended DNS Error Code 1 - Deprecated">
          <t>The requested operation or query is not supported as its
          use has been deprecated. Implementations should not set the
          R flag. (Retrying request elsewhere is unlikely to yield any
          other results.)</t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: REFUSED(5)">
	<section anchor="errlame"
	         title="REFUSED Extended DNS Error Code 1 - Lame">
          <t>An authoritative server that receives a query (with the
          RD bit clear) for a domain for which it is not authoritative
          SHOULD include this EDE code in the SERVFAIL response.  A
          resolver that receives a query (with the RD bit clear)
          SHOULD include this EDE code in the REFUSED
          response. Implementations should set the R flag in this case
          (another nameserver or resolver might not be lame).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="errprohibted"
	         title="REFUSED Extended DNS Error Code 2 - Prohibited">
          <t>An authoritative or recursive resolver that receives a query from
          an "unauthorized" client can annotate its REFUSED message with this
          code. Examples of "unauthorized" clients are recursive queries from
          IP addresses outside the network, blacklisted IP addresses, local
          policy, etc.</t>

          <t>Implementations SHOULD allow operators to define what to set the
          R flag to in this case.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NXDOMAIN(3)">
        <section anchor="errblocked"
	         title="NXDOMAIN Extended DNS Error Code 1 - Blocked">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perfom a DNS query but the
          domain is blacklisted due to a security policy implemented
          on the server being directly talked to. The R flag should be
          set.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NXDOMAIN(3)">
        <section anchor="errcensored"
	         title="NXDOMAIN Extended DNS Error Code 2 - Censored">
          <t>The resolver attempted to perfom a DNS query but the
          domain was blacklisted by a security policy imposed upon the
          server being talked to. Note that how the imposed policy is
          applied is irrelevant (in-band DNS somehow, court order,
          etc). The R flag should be set.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="INFO-CODEs for use with RESPONSE-CODE: NXDOMAIN(3)">
        <section anchor="stalenx"
	         title="NXDOMAIN Extended DNS Error Code 3 - Stale Answer">
          <t>The resolver was unable to resolve answer within its time
          limits and decided to answer with a previously cached
          NXDOMAIN answer instead of answering with an error.  This is
          typically caused by problems on authoritative side, possibly
          as result of a DoS attack. The R flag should not be set,
          since retrying is likely to create additional load without
          yielding a more fresh answer.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="A New Extended Error Code EDNS Option">

        <t>This document defines a new EDNS(0) option, entitled "Extended DNS
        Error", assigned a value of TBD1 from the "DNS EDNS0 Option Codes
        (OPT)" registry [to be removed upon publication:
        [http://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters/dns-parameters.xhtml#dns-parameters-11]</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[Value  Name                 Status    Reference
-----  ----------------     ------    ------------------
 TBD   Extended DNS Error    TBD       [ This document ]]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="New Double-Index Registry Table for Extended Error Codes">
        <t>This document defines a new double-index IANA registry
        table, where the first index value is the RCODE value and the
        second index value is the INFO-CODE from the Extended DNS
        Error EDNS option defined in this document. The IANA is
        requested to create and maintain this "Extended DNS Error
        codes" registry. The codepoint space for each INFO-CODE index
        is to be broken into 3 ranges:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>0 - 3583: Specification required.</t>

            <t>3584 - 3839: First Come First Served.</t>

            <t>3840 - 4095: Experimental / Private use</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>A starting set of entries, based on the contents of this
        document, is as follows:</t>


    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 0 (NOERROR)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">1</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Unsupported DNSKEY</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errbaddnskeyalg" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 0 (NOERROR)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">2</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Unsupported DS Algorithm</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errbaddsalg" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 3 (NOERROR)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">3</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Answering with stale/cached data</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="stalenoerror" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 0 (NOERROR)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">4</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Forged answer</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="forgedanswer" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 0 (NOERROR)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">5</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">DNSSEC Indeterminate</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errindeterminate" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">1</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">DNSSEC Bogus</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errbogus" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">2</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Signature Expired</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errexpired" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">3</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Signature Not Yet Valid</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errprior" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">4</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">DNSKEY missing</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"> <xref target="errnodnskey" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">5</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">RRSIGs missing</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errnorrsig" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">6</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">No Zone Key Bit Set</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errnozonekey" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">7</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">No NSEC records could be obtained</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="nonsec" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">9</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">The SERVFAIL error comes from the cache</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="cachederror" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 2 (SERVFAIL)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">10</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Not Ready.</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="notready" /></t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 3 (NXDOMAIN)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">1</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Blocked</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errblocked" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 3 (NXDOMAIN)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">2</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Censored</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errcensored" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 3 (NXDOMAIN)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">3</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Answering with stale/cached NXDOMAIN data</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="stalenx" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 4 (NOTIMP)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">1</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:"></t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errprohibted" /></t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 5 (REFUSED)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">1</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Lame</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errlame" /></t>
    </list></t>

    <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
    <t hangText="RESPONSE-CODE:"> 5 (REFUSED)</t>
    <t hangText="INFO-CODE:">2</t>
    <t hangText="Purpose:">Prohibited</t>
    <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="errprohibted" /></t>
    </list></t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Though DNSSEC continues to be deployed, unfortunately a
      significant number of clients (~11% according to <xref
      target="GeoffValidation"/>) that receive a SERVFAIL from a
      validating resolver because of a DNSSEC validaion issue will
      simply ask the next (potentially non-validating) resolver in
      their list, and thus don't get any of the protections which
      DNSSEC should provide.  This is very similar to a kid asking his
      mother if he can have another cookie. When the mother says "No,
      it will ruin your dinner!", going off and asking his (more
      permissive) father and getting a "Yes, sure, have a
      cookie!".</t>

      <t>This information is unauthenticated information, and an attacker (e.g
      MITM or malicious recursive server) could insert an extended error
      response into already untrusted data &mdash; ideally clients and
      resolvers would not trust any unauthenticated information, but until we
      live in an era where all DNS answers are authenticated via DNSSEC or
      other mechanisms, there are some tradeoffs. As an example, an attacker
      who is able to insert the DNSSEC Bogus Extended Error into a packet
      could instead simply reply with a fictitious address (A or AAAA) record.
      The R bit hint and extended error information are informational -
      implementations can choose how much to trust this information and
      validating resolvers / stubs may choose to put a different weight on
      it.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank Joe Abley, Mark Andrews, Stephane
      Bortzmeyer, Vladimir Cunat, Peter DeVries, Peter van Dijk,
      Donald Eastlake, Bob Harold, Geoff Huston, Shane
      Kerr, Edward Lewis, Carlos M.  Martinez, George Michelson,
      Michael Sheldon, Petr Spacek, Ondrej Sury, Loganaden Velvindron,
      and Paul Vixie.  They also vaguely remember discussing this with
      a number of people over the years, but have forgotten who all
      they were -- if you were one of them, and are not listed, please
      let us know and we'll acknowledge you.</t>

      <t>I also want to thank the band "Infected Mushroom" for providing a
      good background soundtrack (and to see if I can get away with this!)
      Another author would like to thank the band "Mushroom Infectors". This
      was funny at the time we wrote it, but I cannot remember why...</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6891'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2845' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8094' ?>

      <reference anchor="GeoffValidation"
                 target="http://www.potaroo.net/presentations/2016-06-27-dnssec.pdf">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Validation today">A quick review of DNSSEC Validation
          in today&rsquo;s Internet</title>

          <author fullname="Geoff Huston, APNIC">
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to -01:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Address comments from IETF meeting.</t>

          <t>document copying the response code</t>

          <t>mention zero length fields are ok</t>

          <t>clarify lookup procedure</t>

          <t>mention that table isn't done</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -03 to -IETF 00:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Renamed to draft-ietf-dnsop-extended-error</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -02 to -03:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Added David Lawrence -- I somehow missed that in last
          version.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -00 to -01;</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Fixed up some of the text, minor clarifications.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
